CHAPTER 6

Dutch Slave Trade and
Shipping from Pazhaverkadu,
Devanampattinam and Porto Novo
to Syriam, Jakarta, Aceh and
Banten, 1624-1688

The main reason that induced the Dutch East India Company to obtain slaves from the Tamil Coast was to employ them at the various Dutch factories established in Myanmar. Mattheus Leendersz at Syriam in Myanmar in his letter dated 10 February 1638 to the Dutch factor in Pulicat wrote that ‘Do not forget to send, at the earliest, the slaves that were ordered and an additional 20 slaves if possible, because without them the Dutch Company’s affairs would be severely hindered. Moreover, when you send them, please make sure to include several strapping fellows who could be put to work on any task at Syriam.’1 The Dutch factor in Pulicat was placed under heavy pressure to find the required slaves for export. The large scale export was dependent chiefly upon the local availability and supply through the local agents and merchants. Therefore he contacted several persons to arrange for slaves.

In the records of 1641 one finds that some slaves sent from Pulicat were used by the Dutch factor of Syriam to bribe the Burmese officials. Two young slave girls were sent as gifts to Homoor, a broker in Syriam whose help and assistance the Dutch Company chiefly relied upon for developing commerce.2 The next year (1642) a ship arrived from Pulicat and brought slaves. But after one month, five men and women slaves were found incapacitated for any work and so they were deported back to Pulicat.3 It is interesting to find in the letter of the Dutch factor of Pulicat to Dutch Governor-General in Jakarta dated 30 April 1642 that the price of the returned slaves had been valued (collectively to a total amount of 103 guilders) which they had earlier paid in Pulicat in the Dutch Company account.4

The Dutch factor in Pulicat continued to purchase slaves. Four ships that sailed on 3 March 1644 and another four ships that left on 5 October 1644 carried a total of 7,100 slaves.5 He could obtain plenty of slaves at that time because of the famine that continued to prevail as late as in 1646. The Dutch settlements on the Tamil Coast also remained having a large permanent slave population. There was a continuous interaction among different groups of people interested in slaves. The Dutch had kept many slaves for their own use in the various factories without exporting. Pulicat had 440 slaves as on 17 September 1644 and they were all doing various jobs in the factory of the Dutch Company.6

The Dutch factor in Pulicat could export only 19 slaves on 21 May 1652 since the bad famine conditions were over. As a result there were no slaves available for export.7 In 1654, children were enslaved on a large scale in the English settlement of Madras and they were transported silently to the Dutch factory at Pulicat. This facilitated the slave trade of the Dutch Company greatly.8

According to the letter of the Dutch factor of Pulicat to Jakarta dated 10 July 1664, the slaves of the Tamil Coast constituted the major population in the Dutch factories of Syriam and Ava in Myanmar.9 There had been 826 slaves in Syriam and 1,199 at Ava in 1664.10 Slaves exported from Pulicat had to work in the fields and gardens in Syriam during their spare time. This was enforced by the Dutch in order to help pay and compensate for their upkeep and thus found a way to supplement their maintenance. It is reported by the Dutch factor of Syriam vide his letter dated 18 December 1663 to the factor in Pulicat that the Tamil slaves had sowed a large paddy field which yielded approximately 1,000 cesters (48,000 lb) of rice per season.11 Since the slaves were put to work tirelessly without proper rest, many also absconded, escaped and deserted. It had been reported in the Dutch document that the whereabouts of three such runaway Tamil slaves in 1663 could not be traced in Syriam.12 Many slaves had also fallen ill and they often became sick and a general observation on the health condition of the Tamil slaves had been furnished by the Dutch factor of Ava vide his letter dated 14 November 1663 to the Dutch factor at Pulicat in detail.13

The slaves transported from Pulicat had performed an endless variety of chores in Syriam obviously to the economic advantage of the Dutch Company. The main task of the slaves had been concerned with the maintenance of Dutch ships. There were many carpenters and blacksmiths who were employed in shipbuilding works. A letter of the Dutch Governor-General of Jakarta dated 10 June 1666 to the Dutch factor at Pulicat, mentions four Tamil Muslim sawyers requested to be dispatched in 1666. These men were sent to teach the slaves of the Dutch Company in Syriam to select the quality timber variety for shipbuilding, training to saw timber and also supply the planks required. Thus unskilled slaves had come to be productively employed in shipbuilding and repairing the Dutch Company ships in Syriam.14 According to the letter of the Dutch factor of Syriam dated 18 December 1663 to the factor in Pulicat, Tamil slaves in Syriam had assisted the Dutch on their river voyages to and from Pegu.15 Some slaves trained in wood cutting in Pulicat had also been exported. A mention of this is found in the letter of the Dutch factor of Pulicat to the factor at Syriam dated 17 September 1671. He also stated that these slaves could be sent to the forest in Syriam for chopping wood.16 In the same letter, other transported slaves who were already well trained and employed at the gunpowder factory in Pulicat had also been mentioned. He added that these slaves could be properly employed to refine saltpetre in the Dutch factory at Ava.17

The Dutch factor in Syriam continued to ask for slaves to be supplied from Pulicat. He also mentioned the need to replace those in Syriam who were aged and became sick or were otherwise incapacitated. But it was not always that easy to obtain slaves and so the Dutch factor in Pulicat answered in the negative.18 Owing to a dearth of slaves for export to Syriam, the Tamil slave population at the Dutch factory had dwindled.19 There were only six Tamil slaves in Syriam, four in Ava and two in Pegu as on 12 February 1679.20

It may be worthwhile to ask a question as to why the Dutch in Myanmar desired to have the Tamil slaves. The reason was that the Dutch factories at Syriam, Ava and Pegu in Myanmar were placed under administrative control of the Dutch Governor of Coromandel in Pulicat. The Dutch Company devised a policy with the view to transport slaves from distant places because the greater the distance from their homelands, the less the possibility of slaves absconding from any situation they found intolerable. It is noticed that even this did not work because Tamil slaves had often escaped in Myanmar.

RULES FRAMED FOR SLAVE TRADE BY
THE DUTCH EAST INDIA COMPANY

The Dutch Company attempted to define the master slave relations. It framed certain rules and regulations for the smooth governance of slave trade overseas being introduced from the Tamil Coast. Jan Pietersz Coen, the Dutch Governor was the chief architect in this regard. According to the rules, slave traders must ensure the physical fitness and health of the slaves before finalizing sale to the Dutch Company. One does not know whether this provision was introduced with the motive based on the humanitarian grounds or by commercial considerations. Traders who sold a slave suffering from venereal disease if noticed and reported later, had to refund the full price.21 A slave could be purchased and sold only in the presence of a notary and two independent witnesses. Manumission or freeing of a slave could also be done only in the same manner. These provisions were considered very necessary by the Dutch Company since the purchase and sale of slaves came widely to be conducted illegally on the Tamil Coast. Masters who tortured and ill-treated the slaves had to forfeit them. However, there had been no mention as to the slaves thus forfeited and whether they were freed or taken over by the Dutch Company. Anyone who debauched the slave of another was liable to punishment but there was no prohibition on the debauching of a slave by the master himself. Anyone who caused physical injury, harm and murder of a slave was also awarded severe punishment.22

Local customs and manners prevalent on the Tamil Coast were faithfully followed before export of slaves overseas. Runaway slaves of the Dutch Company were whipped and shut up in cells. Those slaves who harmed or shamed their masters and mistresses were also dealt with similarly. A slave who killed his master or mistress was sentenced to death.23 A slave could complain to a judge against the cruelty meted out to him by his master. A slave left in misery by his own master could be freed by a judge.24 Even if a bold slave had complained one is not sure whether there was any possibility of a fair enquiry. Further, how far the rights of the slaves were protected is a big question. A freed slave was expected to show respect for his master and his descendants at all times. He should take care of his master in case the latter had met with an economic crisis. If the freed slave died without any near blood relatives, the master was entitled to receive one-fourth of his property. These characteristics indicate that the manumitted slaves enjoyed only nominal freedom. Manumission had been thus used by the Dutch East India Company to extract the services and income in perpetuity from the slaves.25 When the Dutch finally closed down the factory in Myanmar the only eleven remaining Tamil slaves (both men and women) were shipped to Jakarta on 28 March 1679.26

THE DUTCH COMPANY SLAVE TRADE
FROM THE NAYAKA KINGDOM OF
GINGEE AND THANJAVUR

The ports of Aalamparavai and of Kunimedu, located ten miles south of it, were important ports of the Nayaka kingdom of Gingee. Devanampattinam (situated 25 miles south of Kunimedu) was the main port settlement of the Portuguese from where they exported saltpetre to Goa.27 The Dutch arrived at Devanampattinam in 1608 and obtained permission from Krishnappa Nayak of Gingee (1597-1624) on 15 October 1608 to trade for two years. The import and export duties were fixed at 4 per cent. The contract was renewed on 29 March 1610 and the payment of customs duties were reduced to 2 per cent on all imports and exports.28 Devanampattinam had a flourishing textile trade connected with the hinterland weaving centres and also within the complex of nearby place called Cuddalore which was located close by, within two miles. Devanampattinam therefore developed extensive overseas trade with many Asian ports and the capital city of Gingee could be reached by two days journey from the port.

It was reported by the Dutch that owing to the famine in November in 1618, three or four children could be purchased for one pagoda at Tirupapuilyur in the environs of Devanampattinam.29 The Dutch began to buy slaves available in the region since 1624 and brought them to Devanampattinam Kunimedu and Aalamparavai. These slaves were transported to the port of Pulicat for export to Jakarta in Indonesia.30

Slaves were not available for purchase since famine conditions improved. As a result the Dutch in Devanampattinam could not export slaves from 1631 to 1634.

Slaves were easily available for export from Devanampattinam though there was a heavy demand for slave labour in Jakarta. The Dutch decided to approach the nayak ruler of Gingee in 1643 to seek official permission to purchase slaves and export them. Philip Baldeaus, the Protestant missionary was sent as envoy to the court. He requested the nayak for permission to purchase and export slaves in the ships of the Dutch East India Company. Since slave trade was banned on the Tamil Coast, the nayak flatly refused, adding that transporting slaves overseas was considered the greatest sin by the Hindus.33 From Dutch records it is evident, however that the company silently purchased a small number of slaves in 1651 and exported them to Jakarta.

TABLE 6.1: EXPORT OF SLAVES IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM
DEVANAMPATTINAM TO JAKARTA, 1624-1630

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1624 | February | Wapen van Rotterdam | 400
1625 | January | Wapen van Rotterdam | 100
1626 | June | Sampan | 20
1626 | June | Jager | 31
1626 | July | Duijf | 38
1626 | March-October | Sampan | 98
1627 | January | Duijf | 200
1627 | February | Valcq | 275
1627 | March | Revengie | 100
1628 | January | Medemblick | 100
1628 | August | Vlielandt | 42
1628 | September | Schiedam | 73
1630 | August | Sampan | 206
TOTAL | | | 1,683

Source: See Note.31

TABLE 6.2: PURCHASED IN KUNIMEDU AND EXPORT
OF SLAVES IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM
DEVANAMPATTINAM TO JAKARTA, 1624-1627

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1626 | September | Cleijn Delft & Jonge Leeuwinne | 224
1627 | January | Duijf & Valcq | 200
1627 | March | Revengie | 37
TOTAL | | | 461

Source: See Note.32

TABLE 6.3: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM DEVANAMPATTINAM
TO JAKARTA, 1635-1636

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1635 | June | Hoorn | 35
1635 | June | Der Veer | 91 (80 men, 11 boys)
1635 | November | Maastricht | 45 (12 men, 33 women)
1636 | October | Leeuwarden | 26 (17 men, 9 women)
TOTAL | | | 197

Source: See Note.34

TABLE 6.4: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM DEVANAMPATTINAM
TO JAKARTA, 1651

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1651 | May | Koe | 11
1651 | October | Os | 16
TOTAL | | | 27

Source: See Note.35

It is found in Dutch records that the company could not purchase slaves nearly for a decade. They managed to purchase slaves in 1660-2 and exported them to Jakarta.

There is a mention that the Dutch ships sailed from Pulicat to Jakarta. Hence slaves procured from the ports of the kingdom of the nayak of Gingee were transported in boats from Devanampattinam, Aalamparavai and Kunimedu to Pulicat. On arrival the ship loaded slaves and sailed away to Jakarta.

TABLE 6.5: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES IN
DUTCH SHIPS FROM DEVANAMPATTINAM
TO JAKARTA, 1660-1662

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1660 | March | Nieuwpoort | 61
1661 | August | Leerdam | 22
1662 | February | Goederhede | 59 (men)
1662 | April | Sampan | 24
TOTAL | | | 166

Source: See Note.36

The Dutch wished to trade at the ports of the Nayaka kingdom of Thanjavur. In 1649 they were permitted when approached by Vijaya Raghava, nayak of Thanjavur (1634-74) to trade at the ports of Tirumullaivasal located at the mouth of river Kollidam. It had access to the immediate hinterland of Sirkali where paddy and rice was available in abundance for export. The Dutch were permitted to trade there and payment of customs duties were fixed by the nayaka ruler at 2½ per cent.

The Dutch mainly explored the purchase of slaves and they bought slaves successfully at the port of Tirumullaivasal in 1644. Though the place of origin of slaves had been from the nearby hinterland villages of Tirumullaivasal, the transportation and boarding in ships had been at Pulicat and the ultimate destination was Jakarta.

The Dutch aimed to participate in slave trade in and around the hinterland of the port of Adirampattinam and Nagapattinam in 1644 since slaves were available for export and it was conducted largely by the private Portuguese traders. According to Dutch Company records, mention had been made that the purchase price of a slave in Adirampattinam and Nagapattinam region in 1645 had become so cheap to the tune of ¾ pagodas and this had lured them mainly to conduct trade. The Dutch managed to purchase slaves easily from Adirampattinam area and exported 2,118 slaves to Jakarta in 1645-6 by nine ships. It is also mentioned that 572 slaves had died on the way at that time because of plague.38

TABLE 6.6: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM TIRUMULLAIVASAL
TO JAKARTA, 1644

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1644 | July | Broeckoord | 47
1644 | August | Lis | 8
1644 | October | Nieuw Amsterdam | 78
TOTAL | | | 133

Source: See Note.37

The port of Karaikal located on the banks of Arasalar was another significant port that flourished under the nayak of Thanjavur and it was located 21 miles south of Tirumullaivasal. The Dutch were permitted to trade there and payment of customs duties was fixed by the nayaka ruler at 2½ per cent. They purchased slaves on a large scale owing to the famine during 1646 and 1647 and sent them in boats to Pulicat for export to Jakarta.

It was found difficult by the Dutch to buy slaves in the region as they were not available. They managed to purchase in small number in 1651 and sent them to Pulicat.

TABLE 6.7: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM TIRUMULLAIVASAL
TO JAKARTA, 1646

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1646 | February | Lis | 79
1646 | September | Grijpskerck | 52
1646 | September | Schiedam & Heemstede | 598
TOTAL | | | 729

Source: See Note.39

TABLE 6.8: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM KARAIKAL
TO JAKARTA, 1646-1647

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1646 | February | Sampan | 40
1646 | March | Sampan | 15
1646 | May | Grijpskerck | 400 (312 men, 88 women)
1646 | May | Haen | 374
1646 | June | Sampan | 100
1646 | June | Salamander | 250
1646 | June | Heemstede | 381
1646 | June | Sampan | 100
1646 | July | Grijpskerck | 300
1647 | October | The Gulden Gans | 16
TOTAL | | | 1,976

Source: See Note.40

TABLE 6.9: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM KARAIKAL
TO JAKARTA, 1651

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1651 | April | Zeerob | 13
1651 | May | Koe | 5
1651 | October | Os | 13
TOTAL | | | 31

Source: See Note.41

LOCAL RULER’S RESISTANCE TO SLAVE TRADE
OF THE DUTCH FROM DEVANAMPATTINAM
AND CUDDALORE TO JAKARTA, 1688

After the death of Krishnappa Nayak, the kingdom of Gingee passed into the hands of the Marathas. Shivaji, the ruler noticed the active slave trade of the Dutch East India Company and he banned the export of slaves from the ports of Devanampattinam, Cuddalore and Porto Novo. He issued a cowle (a written order) in March 1678 and strictly prohibited the Dutch from engaging in slave trade. He stated that under the Sultan of Golconda in Masulipatnam on the Telugu Coast it had been lawful for the Europeans to buy men, women and children as slaves. But so long as he was the master of the land in the Tamil Coast, the Dutch would not buy or transport any men, women and children as slaves.42 Thus it is evident that the Hindu rulers of the coast came to regard transporting Tamil slaves to the overseas as being at odds with Hinduism and against their own conception of human rights. Hence they raised objections and banned the slave trade based on the religious and humanitarian grounds, losing no time to translate it into decisive action. Slave trading by the Dutch had elicited severe reactions from the local government and was found as late as in 1688 on the Tamil Coast.43

SLAVE TRADE OF THE DUTCH FROM PORTO
NOVO TO ACEH IN SUMATRA AND
BANTEN IN JAVA, 1640-1647

Marakkayars began their trade with Aceh in Sumatra in 1640 when they were encouraged by Sultan Iskander Thani (1636-41) the ruler. The Dutch who traded with Porto Novo had also participated in slave trade. During September 1640 5 ships carried a cargo of 150 slaves besides 540 packets of textiles, 20 bales of raw cotton.44 Slave trade also flourished from Porto Novo and one reads about a ship sailing to Aceh with 37 slaves in 1641.45 The slave trade conducted by the Dutch Company gave a boost to the marakkayars to purchase and assist in the export of slaves. Different business strategies came to be pursued by the native slave agents and brokers and these demonstrate how the commerce in human beings was fragmented.

An agent of the Dutch Company was in-charge of bringing slaves from the interior villages of the hinterland of Porto Novo, while another sold them to Dutch, who in certain cases, was in-charge of transportation and held responsible till the ships departed from Porto Novo. It is equally interesting to note the response of the Tamil Muslim merchants.46 The export of slaves had largely continued in 1646 owing to famines. Maxmillan Bowman, an Englishman witnessed the arrival of Tamil slaves in ships to Aceh during the famine and he recorded in October 1646, ‘There came upon this small vessel upward of 400 slaves so hunger starved that they were scarcely able to crawl when they brought them ashore. They were sold at five to six taels (a Chinese weight for silver) per head, at a discount for half the usual price, due to their wretched physical condition.’47 Ships also sailed away to Banten in Java from Porto Novo with 100 slaves in 1646 and the owner of the ship was Ahmad marakkayar. He was exempted from the payment of export duty on the slaves. Meerjung marakkayar a slave dealer who lived at Sirkazhi in the hinterland had arranged for the purchase of slaves. Trade in slaves continued in 1647 and a ship sailed away from Porto Novo to Aceh with many slaves in 1647.48 Thus it to be noted that the port of departure of the ship which transported slaves need not necessarily indicate the place of origin of the slaves.

Maritime scholars opine that documents related to slave trade in the regions of Asia and in the Indian Ocean are scattered and available here and there.49 Hence, the exact nature of slave trade like that in the Atlantic region could not be known and is now therefore called into question. It is certainly possible to know the long term effect of slave trade and human migration in Asia if proper analysis is made by collecting the statistical data from the Dutch records.

The Dutch documents on the Coromandel Coast do not contain details such as age and caste of the slave, the details of the agent or broker who sold the slaves. The price paid had rarely been recorded. It is mentioned that 143 slaves died on the way from Karaikal to Pulicat during transport in a rented vessel in February 1646. Therefore one could understand the pitiable health condition and misery of the slaves. The chapter explains the importance of the particular regions and the individual countries in understanding the specificities of the Indian Ocean slave trade and slavery that need to be highlighted and contrasted with each other, something which had not been highlighted in the numerous works of historians. Slaves were both imported and exported solely for the purposes of slave labour. Before embarking on a comparative study it is therefore necessary to have an understanding of the historical context of the establishment of slavery and the migration of the people in coastal areas through the slave trade. The Dutch in Kunimedu and Devanampattinam had purchased and exported 2,533 slaves for export to Jakarta. They exported 862 slaves from Tirumullaivasal, 2,118 from Adirampattinam and 2,007 slaves from Karaikal. These 7,620 slaves in total had reached were forced to work as labourers in pepper and nutmeg gardens, animal husbandry and fortification works in Jakarta. Slavery in the early modern age was thus a natural and widely accepted institution among human beings. The people were unaware of its moral wrongs until the abolitionist movement that emerged later. A mode of Dutch East India Company slave production had emerged and it was different from the former slavery that was domestic, applied mainly to the slaves owned by the inhabitants. The roles of the Dutch Company slaves were by no means domestic and were crucial to the subsistence, profit and defence of the Dutch settlements. The company was certainly concerned to maximize the productivity of slaves.

NOTES

1. Nationaal Archief (hereafter NA), Den Haag, Mss VOC 1127, fls.190–90v.

2. NA, VOC 1135, fl. 345v, letter of Arent Gardenijs in Pulicat to Hendrick Molijn in Myanmar dated 10 May 1641; VOC 1135, fl. 370 letter of the Dutch factor of Pulicat to Jakarta dated 8 June 1641.

3. NA, VOC 1138, fl.749v.

4. Ibid.

5. NA, VOC 1156, fl. 279; VOC 1147, fl. 574.

6. NA, VOC 1248, fl. 2254.

7. NA, VOC 876, fl. 281.

8. Henry Davison Love, Vestiges of Old Madras, 1640-1800: Traced from the East India Company’s Records Preserved at Fort St. George and the India Office, and from Other Sources, 3 vols., John Murray, London, 1913, vol. I, pp. 127-8, 130-1, 135, 147, 149.

9. NA, VOC 1248, fl. 2030.

10. NA, VOC 1245, fl. 447v.

11. NA, VOC 1242, fl. 726.

12. Ibid.

13. Ibid., fl. 719.

14. NA, VOC 890, fl. 247.

15. NA, VOC 1242, fl. 726v.

16. NA, VOC 1274, fl. 771.

17. Ibid., fl.775.

18. Ibid.

19. NA, VOC 1333, fl. 604v.

20. NA, VOC 1332, fl. 484v.

21. Jan Pietersz Coen, Beschiden Omtrent Zijn Bedirjf in Indie, 7 vols., ed. H.T. Colenbrander, The Hague, 1919-34, vol. 1, pp. 706-8.

22. Pieter van Dam, Beschryvinge van de Oostindische Compagnie, ed. F.W. Stapel and C.W. Th. Van Boetzelaer, 7 vols., ’S Gravenhage, 1927-54, repr., 1977, see vol. II, pt. II.

23. Sudeshna Chakravarti, ‘The Dutch East India Company and Slave Trade in Seventeenth Century India: An Outline by Pieter van Dam, An Advocate of the Company’, Journal of the Asiatic Society of Calcutta, vol. 39, no. 2, 1997, pp. 73-99.

24. Ibid.

25. Ibid.

26. NA, VOC 1348, fl. 1220v.

27. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, Expanding Portuguese Empire and the Tamil Economy: Sixteenth-Eighteenth Centuries, Manohar, New Delhi, 2009, pp. 265-8.

28. Tapan Raychaudhri, Jan Company in Coromandel, 1605-1690: A Study in the Interrelations of European Commerce and Traditional Economies, The Hague, 1962, p. 19.

29. Om Prakash, The Dutch Factories in India: A Collection of Dutch East India Company Documents Pertaining to India, 1617-23, New Delhi, Munshiram, 1984, vol. I, p. 80.

30. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, From European Dwelling Settlements to Global Cities: Ports of the Tamil Coast and the Colonial Modernity, Primus, 2021, pp. 247-50.

31. NA, VOC 1087, fls. 181-181v, NA, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 2 February 1624; DR, 8-11 March 1624, p. 33; VOC 1082, fl. 214, Batavia to Marten Ysbrantsz in Pulicat, 26 March 1624; VOC 1082, fl.135, GM, 27 January 1625; VOC 1087, fl. 198v, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 22 January 1625; VOC 1090, fl. 245v, Marten Ysbrantsz in Pulicat to Batavia, 4 June 1626; VOC 1095, fl. 31, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 21 June 1626; VOC 1095, fl.31v, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 18 July 1626; VOC 1090, fl.113; W.Ph. Coolhas, ed., Generale Missiven van de Gouverneurs-Generaal en Raden Aan Heren XVII der Verenigde Oostindische Compagnie, 9 vols., ’S Gravenhage, 1960-84 (hereafter GM), 13 December 1626; VOC 1095, fl. 35, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 9 January 1627; VOC 1095, fl. 36v, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 4 February 1627; VOC 1095, fl. 37, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 17 March 1627; VOC 1094, fl. 91v, Marten Ysbrantsz in Pulicat to Batavia, 24 January 1628; VOC 1095, fl. 41v, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 31 January 1628; VOC 1095, fl. 46, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 15 August 1628; VOC 1095, fl.17, VOC 1100, fl.100, Marten Ysbrantsz in Pulicat to Batavia, 24 August 1630.

32. NA, VOC 1095, fl. 33, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 20 September 1626; VOC 1095, fl. 35, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 9 January 1627; VOC 1095, fl.37, Pulicat’s Dagregister, 17 March 1627.

33. NA, VOC 1151, fl.764r; VOC 1324, fl. 2r.

34. NA, VOC 1117, fl. 666, Marten Ysbrantsz in Pulicat to Batavia, 19 June 1635; VOC 1117, fls. 667-668, Marten Ysbrantsz in Pulicat to Batavia, 19 June 1635; VOC 1117, fls. 681v, 685v, Carel Reijniersz in Tegenepatnam to Batavia, 2 November 1635; VOC 1119, fl. 1170, Maastricht’s bill of lading; VOC 1119, fl. 1175, 8 October 1636, Leeuwarden’s bill of lading; J.A. Van der Chijs et al., Dagregister Gehouden int Casteel Batavia vant Passerende daer te Plaatse als Over Geheel Nederlandts-India, 1628-1682, 31 vols., The Hague-Batavia, 1887-1928 (hereafter DR), 31 October 1636, p. 262.

35. NA, VOC 1184, fls. 233-233v, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 6 July 1651; VOC 1184, fl. 172, VOC 1184, fl. 346, Os’s bills of lading, Pulicat, 5 October 1651.

36. NA, VOC 1233, fls. 24-24v, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 24 March 1660; VOC 1233, fl. 33, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 6 May 1660; VOC 1232, fl. 381, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Heeren XVII, 9 August 1660; VOC 1236, fl. 594, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 4 August 1661; VOC 1234, fl. 130, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Heeren XVII, 15 September 1661; DR, 18 October 1661, pp. 312-13, 325; VOC 1234, fl.99, GM, 22 December 1661; VOC 1240, fl. 382, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 9 February 1662; VOC 1240, fl.355, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 8 April 1662.

37. NA, VOC 1156, fl. 276, Arnold Heussen in Pulicat to Batavia, 5 October 1644; VOC 1156, fl.281, Arnold Heussen in Pulicat to Batavia, 5 October 1644; VOC 1156, fl.286, Arnold Heussen in Pulicat to Batavia, 5 October 1644; VOC 1156, fl. 298, Nieuw Amsterdam’s bill of lading, Pulicat, 6 October 1644; VOC 1156, fl. 303.

38. NA, VOC 1160, fl. 9; GM, 15 January 1647.

39. NA, VOC 1161, fl.935v, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 19 February 1646; VOC 1161, fl.975, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 8 September 1646; VOC 1164, fl. 731v, Schiedam’s bill of lading, Pulicat, 29 September 1646.

40. NA, VOC 1161, fl. 941, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 9 March 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 941, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 16 March 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 952v, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 1 May 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 826, Arnold Heussen in Pulicat to Batavia, 3 May 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 956, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 19 May 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 962, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 6 June 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 965v, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 10 June 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 795, Arnold Heussen in Pulicat to Batavia, 9 June 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 798, Arnold Heussen in Pulicat to Batavia, 9 June 1646; VOC 1161, fl. 971, Castle Geldria’s Journal, Pulicat, 26 July 1646; VOC 1168, fl. 515v, Arnold Heussen in Pulicat to Batavia, 5 October 1647.

41. NA, VOC 1184, fls. 261, 276, Laurens Pith in Pulicat to Batavia, 18 April 1651; VOC 1184, fl. 233, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 6 July 1651; VOC 1184, fls. 233-233v, Laurens Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 6 July 1651; VOC 1184, fl.172, VOC 1184, fl. 346, Os’s bills of lading, Pulicat, 5 October 1651.

42. K.A. Nilakanta Sastri, ‘Shivaji’s Charters to the Dutch on the Coromandel Coast’, Proceedings of the Indian History Congress, Third Session, Calcutta, 1936, pp. 1156-65.

43. British Library (hereafter BL), London, Oriental and India Office Collection, (hereafter OIOC), G/19/5, fl. 43r; OIOC, MSS Eur. Mackenzie General 55, fls. 46-7; Records of Fort St. George, Diary and Consultation Book, 1672-1746, 1749-57, ed. C.M. Schmidt, J.J. Cotton, A.V. Venkatarama Ayyar, B.S. Baliga et al., 90 vols., Madras, 1910-53, The Diary & Consultation Book of the Honble Elihu Yale Esq President Governour & Councill their proceedings & transactions for the affairs of the Rt. Honble English East India Company in the Presidency of the Coast of Choromandell & the Bay of Bengala, Consultation of 14 May 1688.

44. Dagregister, 1640-1, p. 206.

45. Ibid., p. 215. The ship also carried gunpowder, sugar and rose water.

46. Ibid., pp. 204-7.

47. William Foster, ed., The English Factories in India: A Calendar of Documents in the India Office, British Museum & Public Record Office, vol. I (1618-21), vol. II (1622-3), vol. III (1624-9), vol. IV (1630-3), vol. V (1634-6), vol. VI (1637-41), vol. VII (1642-5), vol. VIII (1646-50), vol. IX (1651-4), vol. X (1655-60), vol. XI (1661-4), vol. XII (1665-7), vol. XIII (1668-9), Oxford, 1906-27 (hereafter EFI), vol. VIII, pp. 54-5.

48. BL, OIOC, Factory Records of Fort. St. George, no. 20, see the letter of English East India Company servant John Davis, Ralph Ingeram and Wilson written from Cuddalore dated 14 May 1687; Thomas Bowrey, A Geographical Account of the Countries around the Bay of Bengal, 1669-79, ed., Sir Richard Temple, Cambridge, 1905, pp. xxxi-xxxiii.

49. S. Arasaratnam, ‘Slave Trade in the Indian Ocean in the Seventeenth Century’, K. S. Mathew, ed., Mariners, Merchants and Oceans: Studies in Maritime History, New Delhi, Manohar, 1995, pp. 195-208, see p. 195.